<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Quilts &#8211; Quilting Clenpot</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/quilts/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>My work in progress quilting site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 14:32:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.0</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Space</title>
		<link>/2022/07/13/space/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 14:55:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=123</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[text and better pictures coming soon&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>text and better pictures coming soon&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pineapple</title>
		<link>/2022/07/13/pineapple/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 14:55:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[text and better pictures coming soon&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>text and better pictures coming soon&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dinosaurs</title>
		<link>/2022/07/13/dinosaurs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 14:36:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=114</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I saw this pattern on Elizabeth Hartman’s website (https://elizabethhartman.com/) and really wanted to try it. I knew it would be a challenge to piece and]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I saw this pattern on Elizabeth Hartman’s website (<a href="https://elizabethhartman.com/">https://elizabethhartman.com/</a>) and really wanted to try it. I knew it would be a challenge to piece and was quite excited because this would be the most complicated pattern that I had ever tried. Fortunately, there was a new baby due in the family soon so that gave me the perfect excuse. The parents preferred muted tones to the bright colours that I am used to making quilts from so I opted for more pastel colours with a background colour of linen texture green. I love working with the baby quilt prints, they are so much fun, I especially enjoyed making a T-Rex out of alien fabric with ducky legs.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Matterhorn</title>
		<link>/2022/07/13/matterhorn/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 14:16:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This quilt was my first attempt at a scenic picture quilt, one day I hope to make a full size one. This one is just]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This quilt was my first attempt at a scenic picture quilt, one day I hope to make a full size one. This one is just a wall hanging measuring about 80cm square, it really looks great on our wall!</p>



<p>To create this quilt, I drew the mountain out onto a grid of 1 inch squares half the size I wanted. I thought that basing the quilt off 2 inch squares would be manageable and would turn out around the size that I wanted. After drawing the mountain, I then adjusted the mountain to as much as possible consist of squares or half square triangles, this would make it much easier to piece. I did end up with some pieces consisting of half rectangle triangles and other irregular squares, but it wasn’t too many, so I just went with it. I used flying geese to depict the trees and 4 inch squares for the sky. I laid out the fabrics on the floor before sewing together so I could get the right colour arrangement before piecing.</p>



<p>For the quilting I did some tree shaped lines for the trees and grassy tufts for the grass hill, some close ups are shown below. The sky I did wobbly lines with a walking foot and the mountain free motion scribbles going the same way that the rock went.</p>



<figure class="wp-container-2 wp-block-gallery-1 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img width="1024" height="768" data-id="109"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/treesAndGrass1-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-109" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/treesAndGrass1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/treesAndGrass1-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/treesAndGrass1-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/treesAndGrass1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/treesAndGrass1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" data-id="110"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/closeUpMatterhorn-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-110" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/closeUpMatterhorn-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/closeUpMatterhorn-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/closeUpMatterhorn-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/closeUpMatterhorn-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/closeUpMatterhorn-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ted in a Bed</title>
		<link>/2022/07/12/ted-in-a-bed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 16:59:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=91</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This quilt I made for a new bairn. It was the first quilt I had made in quite a while, and I did not have]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This quilt I made for a new bairn. It was the first quilt I had made in quite a while, and I did not have many fabrics, but my partner bought me some pink and blue fabrics from Lidl and then I found a yellow fabric to brighten it up some more. Because I had not quilted in quite a bit, I wanted to do a sampler type quilt so I could get back into making lots of different patchwork blocks, lots of my old favourites including churn dash and the old windmill. For the white background of the blocks, I used an old sheet, I wouldn’t recommend this as it was quite thin and I wonder if it will stand the test of time.</p>



<p>For the bears I drew them out first on paper to get the right size then bond-a-webbed and appliquéd them onto the pillow fabric with a zig-zag stich. I hand sewed the eyes and mouths of the parents with a 6-strand embroidery thread. I like how the ear and bow fabrics of the bears appear in the blocks and think the little pink bow was a nice touch.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unicorn with Stars</title>
		<link>/2022/07/12/unicorn-with-stars/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 16:49:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=83</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This quilt I made for a young girl who loves unicorns. The unicorn is a pattern by Elizabeth Hartman (https://elizabethhartman.com/) and I added some star]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This quilt I made for a young girl who loves unicorns. The unicorn is a pattern by Elizabeth Hartman (<a href="https://elizabethhartman.com/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://elizabethhartman.com/">https://elizabethhartman.com/</a>) and I added some star of hope 6 inch blocks and some squares of unicorn fabric to make it bigger along with a nice border of rainbow stary fabric. I found a lovely line of unicorn fabric called Believe by Kim Schaefer and found fabrics from my stash and from the shop to go with them. The finished size is around a metre square. It&#8217;s not possible to tell from the photo but the horn is done with glittery fabric!</p>



<p>Some of my favourite fabrics in this quilt include a blue fabric with rainbows and a constellation pink fabric. I thought these were quite appropriate for a unicorn quilt and hope that the owner enjoys them as much as I did. I wonder if they will see something different in the quilt every time they snuggle under it, I like to try to hide little things in quilts which can&#8217;t be seen unless you really look at it deeply.</p>



<p>I quilted this quilt using stich in the ditch around the unicorn and the star border then added some machined stars in navy on the background for extra security. The backing fabric is a super vibrant flowery print which I really didn&#8217;t buy enough of so had to do a few joins to make it work but it was definitely worth it.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-1024x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-88" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-1024x1024.jpeg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-300x300.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-150x150.jpeg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-768x768.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-1536x1536.jpeg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack-800x800.jpeg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/unicornBack.jpeg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>FMQ Log Cabin</title>
		<link>/2022/07/12/fmq-log-cabin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 14:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=65</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I wanted to make a quilt to practise my free motion quilting, specifically I wanted large areas to practise all over designs along with some]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="651" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/quiltOnBed-1024x651.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-70" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/quiltOnBed-1024x651.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/quiltOnBed-300x191.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/quiltOnBed-768x488.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/quiltOnBed-1536x976.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/quiltOnBed-2048x1301.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>I wanted to make a quilt to practise my free motion quilting, specifically I wanted large areas to practise all over designs along with some smaller areas. I got the idea for this quilt from the book “Free-Motion Quilting with Angela Walters” the quilt is called Housing Project and was designed and pieced by Scott Hansen and quilted by Angela. I had previously practised some of the quilting designs from this book on pieces of scraps and quilted some eggs for easter bunting. I felt like I was ready to move onto trying to quilt something larger and hoped that my sewing machine was up for the challenge and had enough throat space for an almost double bed sized quilt.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/eggs-564x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-105" width="282" height="512" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/eggs-564x1024.jpeg 564w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/eggs-165x300.jpeg 165w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/eggs.jpeg 756w" sizes="(max-width: 282px) 100vw, 282px" /></figure>



<p>I decided on 12 inch log cabins to practise my all over designs. I have heard other quilters say that when quilting large pieces on a domestic quilt they often break it up into 12 inch squares and quilt these one at a time. I sort my scraps by size, so the bag labelled “strips” came out for making the log cabin blocks, I used these along with some wider strips that I cut with some of my favourite fabrics from my stash to help the blocks go together faster. I often find myself with an odd mix of fabrics that do not necessarily “go with” many other fabrics so something like this where anything goes it was the perfect opportunity for me to use them. I let my partner choose the plain fabrics that I was to use for the smaller sections, letting others choose fabric for me forces me to match colours that are not natural for me to match. He choose a light blue and a sand yellow which reminded me of the beach.</p>



<p>For the yellow and blue sections I choose one design for each and stuck with them throughout the quilt. I wanted two designs that I would try to master by the time I had finished. For the yellow I choose feathers, this design includes travelling and echoing and requires a steady hand. I struggled to get my travelling lines to sit directly on my previously quilted line and found the weight of the quilt difficult to manage, the weight kept pulling me off course. I experimented with quilting with my feed-dogs up instead of down the had tension settings set to what I usually use for piecing and just changed my stich length to 0. I found that this stabilised the quilt and made my quilting lines more consistent and smoother. For the blue sections I used a geometric pattern that required quilting with a ruler I liked the pattern but found quilting with a ruler difficult due to the size of the quilt, when I practised on smaller pieces, I found it much easier. By the end I tried to free hand most of the straight lines but because they were spaced out and long this was quite tricky. If I did this design again, I would try to free hand it and do it smaller and in smaller sections.</p>



<p>A lot of the all over designs that I quilted on the log cabin blocks came from my Angela Walters book, I also did some designs from her recent FMQ Challenge “fillers” (<a href="https://www.quiltingismytherapy.com/free-quilt-patterns-and-tutorials/free-motion-challenge-quilting-along/free-motion-fillers-free-motion-challenge-quilting-along/page/2/">https://www.quiltingismytherapy.com/free-quilt-patterns-and-tutorials/free-motion-challenge-quilting-along/free-motion-fillers-free-motion-challenge-quilting-along/page/2/</a>). I also tried some designs that I thought would look good on blocks that I might like to quilt in the future and some text. Two of my favourites are shown below, pebble variations and wavy swirls, I like the textures that these create, and they were not too hard to quilt.</p>



<figure class="wp-container-4 wp-block-gallery-3 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" data-id="67"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bubbles-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-67" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bubbles-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bubbles-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bubbles-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bubbles-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/bubbles-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Bubbles</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" data-id="68"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/wavySwirls-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-68" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/wavySwirls-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/wavySwirls-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/wavySwirls-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/wavySwirls-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/wavySwirls-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Wavy Swirls</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The backing of the quilt is a beautiful cirtus fruit print, I had to add the green polka-dot because there was not quilt enough yet on the roll at the shop.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="768" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/backing-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-71" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/backing-768x1024.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/backing-225x300.jpg 225w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/backing-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/backing-1536x2048.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/backing.jpg 1671w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scrappy Nine Patch</title>
		<link>/2022/07/12/scrappy-nine-patch/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[quilting-clenpot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 10:57:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Quilts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A colourful single bed sized quilt made from 2.5 inch square scraps. Even though the design was simple I could never get bored working with]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A colourful single bed sized quilt made from 2.5 inch square scraps. Even though the design was simple I could never get bored working with fabrics that are so bright and varied, it was a joy to make.</p>



<p>My Mum has a box of scraps cut into 2.5” squares and sorted by colour. I thought a checkerboard design would add some consistency to the vast quantity of random colours so together we matched the squares into pairs of fabric that would complement each other. Choosing fabrics that go together is one of my favourite things about quilting and with scraps it is even more exciting. Every piece has a story as all the fabrics have been pre-used. While matching them up my mum and I reminisced about old quilts that she had made with the fabrics, items of clothes that they had come from or the specific fabric shop that we had bought the fabric from. of choice when matching up the fabrics, they may not go well together but with scraps there may not be other options and I like been forced to use colours that I would not usually put together, it is very exciting. Below are some of my favourite blocks.</p>



<figure class="wp-container-6 wp-block-gallery-5 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1024" data-id="20"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-20" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-768x768.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock1-800x800.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" data-id="21"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock2-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-21" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock2-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock2-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock2-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock2-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/FavBlock2-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
</figure>



<p>We went to the shop to buy the border colour and with this sort of quilt I would usually go for a navy with goes with everything and makes the bright colours really pop. However the pink is incredible, it simultaneously blends into the background and enhances the colours, I think it’s because it’s a warm mid-tone, a light or dark colour would make the blocks stand out individually while this makes the quilt one tying the blocks together. What also helps to tie the blocks together is this amazing circle border fabric, it contains most of the colours in the blocks but contains more warm colours than cold which makes it again blend in with the pick border and not distract from the blocks.</p>



<p>I quilted the quilt by doing little embroideries in some corners. I found a different stich to do in each place which was fun to do and good practise for me. Here are two of my favourites, a flower and a chain stich swirl.</p>



<figure class="wp-container-8 wp-block-gallery-7 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="768" height="1024" data-id="23"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedFlower-768x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-23" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedFlower-768x1024.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedFlower-225x300.jpeg 225w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedFlower-1152x1536.jpeg 1152w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedFlower.jpeg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="768" height="1024" data-id="22"  src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedSwirl-768x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-22" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedSwirl-768x1024.jpeg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedSwirl-225x300.jpeg 225w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedSwirl-1152x1536.jpeg 1152w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/07/embroidedSwirl.jpeg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></figure>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
